So what I'm gonna
do now is I'm
gonna roast one of
my old scripts, but
I'm only gonna talk
you through setups and
payoffs in it. So
here we are. It's
called YouTube's Hard Until
Businesses Do This. And
then the thumbnail says
make boring videos in
it. We're not gonna
bother with the intro.
I'm just gonna start
from the setup, not
the hook, not the
bit that comes before
it. So the setup
of the intro says
this. In this video,
I'll show you why
making boring videos works
now, why they're becoming
the easiest way to
grow business on YouTube,
and why this approach
is only gonna become
more important in 2026.
All right, so the
red is a setup,
the green is a
payoff. So all I've
done here is set
up the main value
of the video, and
that basically just tells
the viewers what to
expect. It's like a
target they know the
content is gonna be
aiming at, and at
that moment in time,
they'll be sitting there
going, I want to
know that, or they
don't. And what we
want that setup to
do is to make
them curious. So they
go, I want that,
which is an art.
And the more you
get to know your
viewers and understand their
problems, the more you
have clients, the more
you'll understand what they
actually care about. And
then what we do
is we transition.
First, let's just look
at what a boring
video actually is and
why they grow businesses
and channels. So a
transition is basically just
a setup.
And then you pay
it off what you
have just set up.
So the intro has
the big overall setups
that we can pay
off at any time
in a video if
we like. They don't
have to be right
at the end.
And then the transitions
are other little setups
that we don't have
to state, we were
gonna cover in the
intro, but it creates
the setup, pay off,
setup, pay off, setup,
pay off that keeps
people interested. So first
let's look at what
a boring video actually
is and why they
grow businesses channels. So
boring videos are what
Nick for reviews to
make over 300K a
month from driving YouTube
viewers to a low
ticket community. They are
what Hamza used to
become one of the
fastest self -help channels.
They're what the Wizard
Liz used. And they
look almost unplanned. They
come across as very
authentic and they can
be of any length.
The visuals in these
videos are almost non
-existent, maybe a whiteboard,
a few scribbles, or
something drawn on a
paper, and yet these
channels crush it for
views and sales. So
I have set up
what is a boring
video, and by the
time this section ends,
the viewer knows. Now,
a lot of people
get really confused by
an early pay off
and I think the
best way to describe
it is like this.
So imagine I've just
said all of this
and I've shown these
visuals to show you
what a boring video
is, and I've said
they don't have, you
know, they're on a
whiteboard, they do this.
You as a viewer
now go, cool, I
get it. Now, if
I continue to go,
so boring videos are
really just about not
doing that much in
the video. And you
can just sit there
and you can talk
to a camera and
you don't need any
fancy editing, and really
it's just about being
yourself on camera, like
you get it, right?
So an early pay
off is often because
you've just said the
exact thing in a
way where any more
explaining you do is
gonna make the viewer
go, get to the
bit you promised a
minute ago, I understand,
hurry up. So if
we were to reorder
this script and it
said, first, let's look
at what a boring
video actually is and
why they grow businesses,
if I just put
that here and said
boring videos are things
with non -existent graphics,
whiteboards, a few scribbles,
and just someone talking
to a camera, and
then I said, Nick
Sherev makes them and
shows them on the
screen, right? And Hamza
used them and the
Wizard Liz uses them,
it's okay,
but they get it.
So they're gonna start
to have that tension
drop, which is gonna
make them go, all
right, all right, get
to the point. And
that's when they say
get to the point,
because the point has
been paid off so
they want their next
one. So what you
need to look out
for is, not just
paying things off early,
but am I over
explaining this? Has the
point been made? And
often when I read
your guys' scripts, I'm
like, delete 10 lines,
you did a good
enough job with your
example. And that's another
thing that makes the
emotion break so powerful
is, I can show
three clips on the
screen for two seconds
and the viewer gets
it, so we don't
need any more. All
right, so then we
move on. So does
that mean all you
need to do is
whip out your camera
and talk off -anticipantly?
Absolutely not, that's the
worst divide out there.
The creators who win
with boring videos aren't
winging it, they're applying
four foundational things that
most people miss. These
are the 20 %
of actions that drive
80 % of the
results that make boring
videos. Right, so that's
kind of a payoff,
and I literally paid
it off straight away.
Does that mean you
need to whip out
a camera? I just
said no. And then
I just continued to
raise the curiosity by
being like, they're doing
these four things, what
are they? Raise the
curiosity again. And then
I set up, so
now I'm gonna show
you what they are
and how to use
them, as well as
why this generates more
sales over the long
term. So now they
know, this is a
transition, I set up
as a transition, so
they know, okay, I
get why I need
to listen to this
now, and they're back
in. And then what
we do is we
jump in with, okay,
so the first four
foundations of a boring
video that's gonna grow
your channel, harnesses something
called viewer expectation.
Now, I have technically
paid off something there,
and you could argue
that a viewer, a
more experienced creator, would
turn around and go,
I know where this
is going, cool, get
to the point. But
I also know that
most people watching have
absolutely no idea what
that actually means. And
in this case, because
I know my audience,
I can pay something
off to create more
curiosity. So the first
foundations of a boring
video will grow your
channel, harnessing something called
viewer expectations, and messing
this up is one
of the biggest reasons
your videos didn't grow.
So I want them
going, hmm, think I
know what that is,
but it sounds important.
Or, oh, that sounds
interesting. So I actually
paid off what it
was for the avatar
I want, it's not
a payoff. And then
I say, so let
me show you how
this works. So it's
another setup.
Which of these videos
generated hundreds, so now
I'm giving an example,
where the answer is,
blah, blah, blah. So
I show them how
it works with an
example, and that's the
emotion brick. And then
I get here, and
I've finished that explanation,
and it's all paid
off. And then I
set up the next
foundational element, so we've
moved on to the
next bit of advice,
which is a transition,
aka a setup.
They're designed so you
can listen to the
background. Okay, so the
next foundational element that
makes a boring video
work is that they're
not designed to be
watched. They're designed so
you can listen to
the background when making
dinner, or when you're
going to run, they're
basically podcasts. What I
have done there is
paid off too early.
I've said the next
foundational element is making,
it's making, it's making,
it's making it so
you can listen to
them. I mean, think
about this. You're watching
this going, yeah, I
get it.
So I did intentionally
pay off early, and
say they're basically just
audio experiences,
because I didn't need
to explain anything else.
I didn't need to
give an example. I
didn't need to use
a motion brick. It's
just such basic information
that I know my
viewers will be like,
yeah, I listen to
videos all the time.
So I just say
that this gives the
content an advantage,
and then I move
on. So that is
an entire point in
one of my videos.
It's pretty much all
set up and then
a tiny bit of
information. But it's a
critical part because it
plays a key in
one of the foundations
I'm teaching, but there's
just not much to
say so I don't
bother stringing it out.
And that's a trap
you have to avoid.
A lot of people
are like, we need
to have lots of
watch time on YouTube.
We don't. We need
viewer satisfaction. Go and
look at the comments
below my videos and
the amount of people
who are like, you
get everything across so
quick because we don't
need that many words.
And then we have
the third foundation, reducing
what's known as cognitive
load. So again, this
is a set up
for the section. People
are like, oh, and
then I've paid off.
It's about cognitive load.
For exactly the same
reason as I paid
something off early. Because
I know my avatar
either understands that word
a bit or has
no understanding at all.
So I thought, screw
it. I'll pay it
off early then explain
it because they still
want to know what
the heck that even
means. And then I
say, so you've probably
been told to give
a ton of value
in every video, blah,
blah, blah.
And then that's the
section done.
Now, I'm going to
show you another early
payoff I used here
because I think a
lot of people are
scared that they're going
to pay something off
early. You just have
to ask if you
ever pay something off,
just go, do they
still want to know
something or should I
set something else up?
That's it. So I
say, so teaching isn't
about dumping everything you
know, it's about making
key ideas stick. And
the best boring videos
do this in three
ways. First, three, two,
one. I'm going to
show you how to
do it. Pay attention
to that. I'm a
guy who always gives
threes. First, they often
tell a lot of
stories. So I've paid
off the feature. And
do you know what?
This sentence here is
now plummeting in tension.
Stories teach people about
spiking cognitive load, meaning
someone could be cooking
diner. Right? So I've
kept it very short
after that. The style
of this video is
basically a list of
call. And I know
when I'm starting a
list of call, I'm
not going to go
in depth into every
single thing I say.
Really, the biggest point
of it is to
give people one thing
they walk away with
because they don't really
listen to everything or
take everything in. So
in this section of
the video, right, I'm
like talking about three
things they do. And
I could have made
an hour long video
about this. But really,
I'm like, let's just
get the thing moving.
So I say, first,
they tell a lot
of stories. I could
have moved on and
then go, then they
use something called the
rule of threes. And
then they do something
like, right. But I
just decided to add
a little bit more
info there. And it's
two lines. If the
tension drops, the viewers
aren't going to be
going, get to that
point. They'll tolerate a
line or two. And
then I say, and
then they use something
called the rule of
threes. Now that's a
payoff, but it's a
curiosity spiking payoff because
you're probably like, what's
the rule of three?
So we've re -hooked
them with a payoff.
And then I say,
and then finally they
use boring, almost childlike,
simple visuals. I don't
need to say anything
after this. That's a
payoff. And I know
it's a payoff because
I literally showed that
at the start of
my video. So I
don't need this line.
I could have just
showed the visual and
moved on. I wanted
to make a point
to go a little
bit deeper on this.
And because I would
then showed visuals, which
backed up what I'm
saying, it gave them
an idea as to
what I mean, right?
So I'm talking about
childlike, simple visuals. I
re -bring this in.
So again, it's just
a decision. There's no
wrong or right here.
All I know is
I've paid it off.
So I'll bet flipping
set something up quick
because the curiosity is
going to be dropping.
And then you can
see it's a few
lines with a bit
of visuals and I
go, and that moves
us onto the final
foundation to get results
with boring videos. And
I think it's one
of the most underrated
secrets of success.
So that's another setup.
And then basically I
unpack it here. Hamza
in particular was a
master of this. So
I show an example
and here I'm dragging
out the payoff. So
I show the example
before I say what
it is, right? All
I'm saying is this
is one of the
most underrated secrets of
success. And I'm not
going to tell you
what it is yet.
Have a watch this
video, then I'll explain
it after.
I play the clip
and then I still
don't say what it
is. I say, so
when you make videos,
do you worry? What
if someone argues with
what I say in
the comments? What if
people don't believe me?
So here I'm intentionally
trying to log out
the video now and
keep them curious because
they've played a clip.
Now they're going, right,
tell me what it
is. And then I'm
setting up the problem
they have. And then
I say, when you
think like this, it
comes across and I'm
basically starting to unpack
the payoff very slowly.
So when you think
like that, it comes
across in a way
that you present and
the words that you
say, and this massively
impacts your own credibility.
So for example, if
you say maybe this
will work for you
and now I'm slow,
the viewers slowly starting
to understand, ah, I
get where he's going
with this. Or if
you can't get amazing
results, that lack of
certainty will wreck your
credibility. Whereas if you
switch your words to,
so this whole section
is a really drawn
out flipping payoff, but,
but Ed, why did
you decide to do
that? Well, because I
thought of a very
easy way of doing
it. If I'm totally
honest, half the time
I pay something off
earlier and move on.
Cause I think I
can't think of anything
creative to make this
point, just move on
to the next one
and maybe make the
next one a bit
more creative.
So that's another thing
you're going to go
through that too. And
I know a lot
of you are like,
how do I make
every single point super
creative? Like I don't
do that. We skip,
we focus on some,
we move on because
we've got to get
these bad boys out.
Right? So then I
just summarize it as
a slight payoff. I've
unpacked all this stuff
from Hamza. And then
I just. I just
say this line to
finish it off and
that's it. So if
you're going to get
anything from this is
this don't worry if
you pay something off
early, if you pay
something off early and
then you keep explaining
it, that's a problem.
If you pay something
up early and then
you instantly set up
something else, you've re
hooked him. It's fine.
So we just never
want to have nothing
left in the viewers
brains that they don't
want to know the
answers to. And as
you might've picked up
from talking, this is
this is a drill,
but here's the thing.
talking about this you
get better at this
by working with your
clients and getting to
know your viewers because
i know you guys
quite well because i
spend so many hours
in discord and i
hear the questions so
i'm just writing to
you and this is
another thing about really
understanding your avatar and
not trying to solve
too many people's problems
and just positioning around
one problem right we
can't possibly get to
understand hundreds of different
people so i'm writing
to a very particular
person and then i'm
saying would they understand
the meaning of that
word and make it
a payoff no cool
i'll keep educating if
the answer is yes
i'll set something else
up